Finding Aid for Michigan Imprints Inventory records, 1936-1941
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Michigan Imprints Inventory records 1936-1941
Michigan Historical Records Survey.
5 linear feet
851852 Ca 2
Project of the Work Projects Administration in Michigan. Notes on books and pamphlets published in Michigan between 1796 and 1876.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The records were deposited in the Clements Library by the Michigan Historical Records Survey (donor no. 862 ) in 1942. They were later transferred to the Michigan Historical Collections.
No further additions to the records are expected.
The collection is open to research.
The Michigan Imprints Inventory is Michigan's portion of the American Imprints Inventory, a project of the Historical Records Survey of the 1930s and early 1940s. The American Imprints Inventory was begun in 1936 under the direction of Douglas McMurtrie, with the purpose of creating an inventory of early books, serials, and broadsides printed in the United States. The date limit for works to be inventoried varied initially from region to region, but was later revised to include all works printed before the end of 1876.
Historical Records Survey offices in each state conducted the inventory. The inventory was prepared by sending researchers to libraries, where they copied catalog records for all books, serials, and broadsides printed before the cutoff date. Descriptions were prepared in two formats. Works were first described following "Style B," which generally used standard library cataloging conventions. At the request of the national office, older works and works not appearing in standard bibliographies were later re-described, following "Style A," a form of rare book cataloging indicating line ends and ornaments, but not collations. The intent was to publish bibliographies of Style A descriptions for early imprints of each state and major city.
Inventory slips were sent by the state offices to the American Imprints Inventory office in Chicago, where a number of state and city bibliographies were edited and published. When McMurtrie resigned as director in 1941, the imprints inventory project ended at the national level. At that time, inventory slips were returned to the state Historical Records Survey offices in several states, including Michigan, for final editing and publication. The Style A descriptions were edited back to Style B, and the states published "preliminary checklists" covering the work done to that point.
The record group, a single series of records, is made up of three subseries as well as a number of smaller groupings of materials. The three subseries are Imprints by date; Imprints by city; and Imprints by checklist number. The smaller groupings include an inventory of state documents, 1851-1878; slips for works not included in the checklist, questionable and phantom imprints, and other problems; and some correspondence and project manuals.
Imprints by date, 1796-1860 (Boxes 1-2) includes inventory slips, most in Style B, arranged by date. Within each year, the slips are in random order.
Imprints by city, 1796-1876 (Boxes 2-4) includes inventory slips, most in Style B, arranged by city and within each city by date. Within each year, the slips are in random order.
Imprints by checklist number, 1796-1850 (Box 5) includes inventory slips for works listed in the published checklist, most in Style A, with editorial notes used in preparing the checklist.
The Michigan Historical Records Survey also published a checklist of New Mexico imprints, but it had been edited elsewhere and no records of this publication are found in the records of the Michigan Imprints Inventory.
Subjects:
American imprints inventory.; Michigan--Bibliography.; Michigan Historical Records Survey.; Michigan imprints inventory.; Publishers and publishing--Michigan.; United States. Work Projects Administration.
- Records of Imprints Inventory
  - Imprints by date, 1796-1860
    - 1796-1851 (Box 1)
    - 1852-1860 (Box 2)
  - Serials by date, 1844-1876 (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous slips (Box 2)
    (includes slips for newspapers, blank forms, printers, problem items, etc.)
  - Imprints by city, 1796-1876
    - Adrian-Ann Arbor (to 1871) (Box 2)
    - Ann Arbor (from 1872) - Lansing (to 1861 (Box 3)
    - Lansing (from 1862) - Zeeland; and Michigan, no city (Box 4)
  - Imprints by checklist number, 1796-1850, 7 folders (Box 5)
  - Questionable imprints, Published as Appendix (Box 5)
  - Questionable imprints, not published (Box 5)
  - State documents, 1851-1878, 3 folders (Box 5)
  - Miscellaneous imprints (Box 5)
  - Correspondence and notes regarding imprints (Box 5)
  - Manuals and instructions (Box 5)
Bibliography
Publications of the Michigan Imprints Inventory
Preliminary Check List of Michigan Imprints, 1796-1850 (Detroit: Michigan Historical Records Survey Project, 1942)
[Bentley call number EX/5/H673/P924]
Check List of New Mexico Imprints and Publications, 1784-1876(Detroit: Michigan Historical Records Survey Project, 1942).
[not part of Bentley Library holdings]
Catholic University masters' theses based upon American Imprints Inventory records housed at the Library of Congress
Ruddon, Elaine Marie. "A Preliminary Checklist of Non-Official Imprints for the State of Michigan, 1851-1855" (1951)
[not part of Bentley Library holdings]
Sammons, Vivian O. "A Checklist of Michigan Statewide Imprints for the Years 1856-1858" (1966).
[not part of Bentley Library holdings]
Collins, Sara D. "A Check-List of Non-Official Michigan Imprints for the Years 1859 and 1860 with a Historical Introduction" (1966).
[Bentley call number EX/5/C713/C514]